<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-16T19:20:28-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Spyros Simotas, PhD Candidate &amp;amp; Praxis Fellow, University of Virginia</title><subtitle>Freelance Digital Designer &amp; Front-end Developer, Belfast</subtitle><author><name>Spyros Simotas</name></author><entry><title type="html">Site Creation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/2017/06/18/about/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Site Creation" /><published>2017-06-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-06-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/2017/06/18/about</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/2017/06/18/about/">&lt;p&gt;After many attempts to build a static generated website, I have finally found a custom template made by &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckvr.com/&quot;&gt;Michael Mckeever&lt;/a&gt;. Adopting it meant a lot of tweaking but I am pretty happy with the result. For now! Here’s some information about what lies under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build&quot;&gt;Build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website has been built with &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator created by Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;css&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site is built with &lt;a href=&quot;http://tachyons.io/&quot;&gt;Tachyons&lt;/a&gt;, an atomic CSS framework. Paired with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/gulp-uncss&quot;&gt;gulp-uncss&lt;/a&gt; which strips out any unused css, the minified CSS is only 17kb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;typography&quot;&gt;Typography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Headings are typeset in Garamond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paragraph text is set in system fonts so the typeface you see will depend on what platform you’re viewing this on. I’m on a mac, so I see Apple’s system font, San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why system fonts? Well, for speed mostly, but they also look great so I don’t think I’m sacrificing design for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hosting&quot;&gt;Hosting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site is hosted for free on Github pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gulp&quot;&gt;Gulp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gulpjs.com/&quot;&gt;Gulp&lt;/a&gt; is used to automate certain tasks such as minifying and concatenating javascript, minifying CSS and inlining in the head of the document, and watching for changes to rebuild/reload the browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;images-and-icons&quot;&gt;Images and icons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images are hosted locally and loaded dynamically using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aFarkas/lazysizes&quot;&gt;lazysizes.js&lt;/a&gt;. Images are compressed using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/tinypng-cli&quot;&gt;tinypng-cli&lt;/a&gt;. I opted for this over a lossless alternative such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/gulp-imagemin&quot;&gt;gulp-imagemin&lt;/a&gt; because of the superior compression it afforded. The difference was pretty staggering. Icons are loaded via an SVG sprite in the document header.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Spyros Simotas</name></author><summary type="html">After many attempts to build a static generated website, I have finally found a custom template made by Michael Mckeever. Adopting it meant a lot of tweaking but I am pretty happy with the result. For now! Here’s some information about what lies under the hood.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Working at Scholars’ Lab Makerspace, pt. 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/makerspace,/3d/printing,/personal/2017/06/15/Working-at-the-SLab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Working at Scholars’ Lab Makerspace, pt. 1" /><published>2017-06-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-06-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/makerspace,/3d/printing,/personal/2017/06/15/Working-at-the-SLab</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/makerspace,/3d/printing,/personal/2017/06/15/Working-at-the-SLab/">&lt;p&gt;Last fall, having no prior experience in 3D printing, I joined the team of Makerspace technologists. Maybe that’s something nobody’s supposed to know, but it’s true. I began assisting at the Makerspace with only &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/shane-lin/&quot; title=&quot;Shane's Scholar's Lab Profile&quot;&gt;Shane&lt;/a&gt;’s super-comprehensive presentation on 3D printing, which is the activity that attracts the most students to the SLab. Shane’s knowledge and competency, both historical and technical, had me wondering what I had gotten myself into. But as he kept speaking, using words I had never heard before, a whole new dimension had started to rise. Words like slicer, .stl file and GCode, layer height and infill, PLA and ABS, extruder, nozzle size, and bed leveling, had started to layer up in the inevitable Z axis! 
Luckily, the first day on the job was painless. No incidents. No mishaps. No failures. No adhesion or warping problems. No blocked nozzles requiring cold pulling. As a matter of fact, given the uncomplicated nature of my first print, there was no reason for things to go wrong. The command was for a small and uncomplicated cylinder tube. I sliced the .stl file with Cura, then loaded the GCode to the Ultimaker2 and I had basically done my job! It was now up to the machine to translate the GCode into movements in the X, Y, and Z axes by pouring hot plastic in the process. Indeed, after the nozzle was hot enough (over 200ºC) to let the filament come through in liquid form, a motor started to push it into the extruder as it started piling up circle after circle every .2mm. The process may sound tedious, but it is also mesmerizing. There is something exciting and soothing at the same time, to let yourself get lost in the paths of the printer’s head. And its music! 
So, that first print didn’t last long, as most prints usually do. The actual size of the cylinder tube was a few centimeters long. In less than 30 minutes, the tube was erected on the heated bed, ready to be peeled off. In less than 30 minutes, a small physical object had come into being and was now departing in the hands of my first happy patron.&lt;br /&gt;
Since that first print, I can’t say  the same seamless process reflects Makerspace’s reality. Most commonly, success comes as the result of many aborted attempts, tweaking, and recommendations from more experienced makers. Due to all kinds of unexpected technical failures, with adhesion probably being the #1, I have learned to tame my enthusiasm until the final layer is applied, and to use glue! More importantly, I have learned to observe more experienced makers and absorb their know-how and admirable problem-solving skills. Certainly, 3D printing is not rocket science (although it helps you build rockets, right &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/duy-nguyen/&quot; title=&quot;Duy's Scholar's Lab Profile&quot;&gt;Duy&lt;/a&gt;?), but it can be quite frustrating if a significant number of parameters don’t line up. There is an artisanal quality to 3D printing that I didn’t expect existed. The attitude is to preserve the right amount of detachment from the final results and keep experimenting. And in your darkest hour of troubleshooting, it is useful to put things in perspective through poetry: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cavafy.com/poems/content.asp?cat=1&amp;amp;id=74&quot; title=&quot;Cavafy - Ithaca&quot;&gt;Hope the voyage is a long one&lt;/a&gt;.” For that reason, Makerspace offers exposure, good mentorship, an amazingly friendly and playful learning environment, as long as unlimited stocks of filament!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Spyros Simotas</name></author><summary type="html">Last fall, having no prior experience in 3D printing, I joined the team of Makerspace technologists. Maybe that’s something nobody’s supposed to know, but it’s true. I began assisting at the Makerspace with only Shane’s super-comprehensive presentation on 3D printing, which is the activity that attracts the most students to the SLab. Shane’s knowledge and competency, both historical and technical, had me wondering what I had gotten myself into. But as he kept speaking, using words I had never heard before, a whole new dimension had started to rise. Words like slicer, .stl file and GCode, layer height and infill, PLA and ABS, extruder, nozzle size, and bed leveling, had started to layer up in the inevitable Z axis! Luckily, the first day on the job was painless. No incidents. No mishaps. No failures. No adhesion or warping problems. No blocked nozzles requiring cold pulling. As a matter of fact, given the uncomplicated nature of my first print, there was no reason for things to go wrong. The command was for a small and uncomplicated cylinder tube. I sliced the .stl file with Cura, then loaded the GCode to the Ultimaker2 and I had basically done my job! It was now up to the machine to translate the GCode into movements in the X, Y, and Z axes by pouring hot plastic in the process. Indeed, after the nozzle was hot enough (over 200ºC) to let the filament come through in liquid form, a motor started to push it into the extruder as it started piling up circle after circle every .2mm. The process may sound tedious, but it is also mesmerizing. There is something exciting and soothing at the same time, to let yourself get lost in the paths of the printer’s head. And its music! So, that first print didn’t last long, as most prints usually do. The actual size of the cylinder tube was a few centimeters long. In less than 30 minutes, the tube was erected on the heated bed, ready to be peeled off. In less than 30 minutes, a small physical object had come into being and was now departing in the hands of my first happy patron. Since that first print, I can’t say the same seamless process reflects Makerspace’s reality. Most commonly, success comes as the result of many aborted attempts, tweaking, and recommendations from more experienced makers. Due to all kinds of unexpected technical failures, with adhesion probably being the #1, I have learned to tame my enthusiasm until the final layer is applied, and to use glue! More importantly, I have learned to observe more experienced makers and absorb their know-how and admirable problem-solving skills. Certainly, 3D printing is not rocket science (although it helps you build rockets, right Duy?), but it can be quite frustrating if a significant number of parameters don’t line up. There is an artisanal quality to 3D printing that I didn’t expect existed. The attitude is to preserve the right amount of detachment from the final results and keep experimenting. And in your darkest hour of troubleshooting, it is useful to put things in perspective through poetry: “Hope the voyage is a long one.” For that reason, Makerspace offers exposure, good mentorship, an amazingly friendly and playful learning environment, as long as unlimited stocks of filament!</summary></entry></feed>